effects of tongue scraping on plaque
gingivitis and Cavities this is the
first of a five video series on tongue
cleaning what is tongue scraping and is
it the most effective way to clean our
tongue watch this series to find out
[Music]
in my last video series on halitosis I
explored the benefits of eating a high
fiber diet for causing a reduction of
halitosis this effect is thought to be
due to the self-cleaning of the mouth
while chewing food however soft foods
like almost fast food is designed so you
can gulp it down do not sufficiently
scrape at the coating on your tongue and
so you can be left with a tongue coating
a whitish gray layer of debris and
microorganisms particularly towards the
back of your tongue during the
putrefaction of debris on the tongue
volatile sulfur compounds are created
like the rotten egg gas hydrogen sulfide
this putrefaction process may be
responsible for up to 90 percent of bad
breath I did a video on dietary tweaks
to lessen the formation of these
compounds in the first place
but if you're unwilling or unable to
change your diet natural self-cleaning
mechanisms might not necessarily remove
the tongue coating if it's really thick
in which case mechanical tongue cleaning
can remove debris but often tongue
cleaning is not considered a routine
part of oral hygiene should it be
let's find out unless you have some
pocket of pus from like periodontal
disease the most likely source of bad
breath is the surface of your tongue and
it's not like there's one bad actor
bacteria dozens of different bacteria
can produce the same volatile sulfur
compounds from the sulfur-containing
amino acids concentrated in animal
protein that's why probiotics may fail
to change the emissions in fact if you
compare the tongue microbiome and
healthy subjects versus those with bad
breath they have almost the same
bacterial composition so it may be less
which type of bacteria you have on your
tongue and more the sheer quantity of
how many bacteria you have living there
population studies suggest that the use
of tongue scrapers is associated with
less severe symptoms of halitosis but
maybe those who use tongue scrapers are
also more scrupulous about oral hygiene
and other ways the only way to know for
sure is to put it to the test
first though some background tongue
scraping and brushing have been
practiced for centuries many continents
around the world but it's been almost
unknown elsewhere why clean your tongue
ask this editorial in the general
American Dental Association dentists
hygienists and manufacturers of
toothpaste toothbrushes and floss have
long emphasized the need to remove
Dental plaque from your teeth to prevent
cavities but why do so many Americans
produce two Immaculate shining rows of
teeth separated by an organ covered with
millions of microorganisms emitting a
strong Mal odor first of all though what
might be the effect of tongue brushing
on formation of dental plaque like if
you stop brushing your teeth completely
would it matter if you brush your tongue
no stop brushing your teeth and the
plaque builds up either way yeah but
what if you continue brushing but just
add tongue brushing along with tooth
brushing
no effect on the buildup of plaque on
your teeth suggesting that majority of
the important plaque forming bacteria
might not originate from the tongue
though another reason for not finding an
effective tongue brushing on plaque
formation may be that brushing of the
back of the tongue is difficult because
it can make you gag
what about gingivitis gum inflammation
those who clean their tongues tend to
have less bleeding on probing suggesting
healthier gums but you don't really know
if it's cause and effect until you put
it to the test a randomized controlled
clinical trial tongue scraping versus no
tongue scraping and
it made no significant difference
what about tongue scraping as a means to
reduce the acid-producing bacteria that
cause cavities called strep mutans this
study showed a beneficial effect
compared to using a Listerine brand Oral
Care strips or salt water rinses but
this other study found no significant
effect maybe the population of bacteria
is just so large that scraping removed
only a small portion or maybe it's like
sweeping a rug where you're just kind of
moving stuff around the bottom line is
that studies investigating the role of
tongue brushing and plaque accumulation
or gum inflammation show conflicting
results and so on the basis of the
medical research there appears to be no
data that justify the necessity to clean
the tongue on a regular basis ah but the
one exception would be oral Mal odor it
works for combating bad breath which
we'll explore next
foreign